Jonathan Krause Rare Newspaper and Magazine Collection 1648-1881 E302.1 .J76 E302.1 .J76
Lilly Library
- 19th Century American Individuals
  - Civil War Period
    - Abraham Lincoln
      - ADDRESS OF THE COLORED PEOPLE OF THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA TO PRESIDENT LINCOLN, New York Herald, November 3, 1862 (Item 1064)
        In the scandalous meeting at the White House in August with some free blacks, Lincoln contemned and undignified them, deemed them the cause of the war, said black and white could never live together, and desired them to emigrate to certain distant shores (such as Chiriqui, Panama) where they could live peaceably and autonomously, the achievement of which would be assisted by the governement (see Item 819). Now, three months later, they are waiting to hear from Lincoln. This is happening only two months after the Preliminary Emancipation Proclamation. On December 31, 1862, the night before the main Emancipation Proclamation was to go into effect, Lincoln was meeting with Bernard Kock, a shady operator, to discuss colonization (self-deportation) plans for the free blacks. On April 16, Lincoln delivered a proclamation -- a repudiation of an agreement with Bernard Kock. On February 1, 1864, Lincoln issued an executive order -- regarding the colonization experiment, ending his hopes to relocate the free black population of America outside its borders. Lincoln's views on colonization are revealed in the 1861, but especially the 1862 state of the union message.
      - MESSAGE OF CONGRATULATIONS TO THE ARMY OF THE POTOMAC AFTER BATTLE OF FREDERICKSBURG, New York Herald, December 24, 1862 (Item 1005)
        Comments from Mr. Krause: Unlike after the Battle of Gettysburg, where Lincoln could still produce the Gettysburg Address, he was particularly devastated by the losses and senseless slaughter of Fredericksburg which caused him to fall into a slough of despond that worried everybody around him, and contributed to the flat and uninspiring message to the troops-so uncharacteristically un-Lincolnian.
      - EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, New York Herald, January 3, 1863 (Item 824)
      - LETTER TO GENERAL MCCLELLAN AND TWO GENERAL ORDERS AND MCCLELLAN LETTER TO GENERAL BANKS, Daily Richmond Examiner, January 28, 1863 (Item 1065)
        The letter to McClellan is almost a year old. It was likely not released at the time due to its controversial nature, as it would not be helpful to the war effort to see the President dressing down his general for not being aggressive enough in trying to take Richmond. Appearing in one of the most prominent southern papers, it was meant to embarrass Lincoln. In the end, Lincoln allowed McClellan to have his way with disastrous results. Their contentious relationship began even before Lincoln was president. McClellan took every opportunity to insult Lincoln, who eventually removed him from command. They never reconciled, especially after McClellan lost the presidential election to Lincoln. The general orders also from the period of the letter, referring to the General's dilatoriness.
      - LETTER TO MANCHESTER, ENGLAND WORKINGMEN, The Liberator, March 6, 1863 (Item 825)
      - THE UNION LEAGUE GREAT POPULAR DEMONSTRATION, A PLEA FOR THE SOUTHERN UNIONISTS - AN EXPOSE OF COMPROMISERS AND TRAITORS, ADDRESS OF ANDREW JOHNSON, ANNOUNCING DRAFT OF NEGROES, DEPUTATION FROM INHABITANTS OF BIRMINGHAM TO LINCOLN EXPRESSING HORROR AT FORMATION OF CONFEDERACY, The New York Times, March 15, 1863 (Item 991)
      - SIEGE OF VICKSBURG, New York Tribune, April 1, 1863 (Item 826)
      - PROCLAMATION ON THE AFRICAN SLAVE TRADE, The Age, April 25, 1863 (Item 827)
      - LETTER ON MILITARY ARRESTS AND CONSTITUTION, New York Herald, June 15, 1863 (Item 828)
      - PROCLAMATION FOR DAY OF THANKSGIVING AND PRAYER, Star in the West, July 25, 1863 (Item 829)
      - LETTER TO GOVERNOR SEYMOUR AFTER NEW YORK DRAFT RIOTS ON DRAFT LAW, SUPREME COURT AND CONSTITUTION, New York Times, August 10, 1863 (Item 830)
      - LETTER TO CONKLING DEFENDING EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, New York Times, September 3, 1863 (Item 831a)
      - LETTER TO CONKLING DEFENDING EMANCIPATION PROCLAMATION, The Liberator, September 11, 1863 (Item 831b)
      - LETTER TO GRANT ADMITTING LINCOLN MADE A WRONG TACTICAL SUGGESTION, Army and Navy Journal, September 5, 1863 (Item 1037)
      - PROCLAMATION SUSPENDING HABEAS CORPUS, The Waterbury American, September 18, 1863 (Item 832)
      - LETTER TO GOVERNOR ON MARYLAND ELECTION, New York Evening Post, November 5, 1863 (Item 833)
      - LINCOLN LETTER ON WESTERN VICTORIES AND ARMY OF THE WEST, New York Times, December 4, 1863 (Item 1066)
      - PROCLAMATION OF AMNESTY AND RECONSTRUCTION, Army and Navy Journal, December 12, 1863 (Item 1038)
        See item 839 very last speech of Lincoln.
        Shows Lincoln was ruminating on reconstruction as early as 1863. There is also an important report by Secretary of War Edwin Stanton.
      - LETTER TO HODGES, LINCOLN DEFINES HIS POSITION ON SLAVERY AND THE CONSTITUTION, The Crisis, May 4, 1864 (Item 835)
      - IMPROMPTU SPEECH AFTER RENOMINATION, New York World, June 10, 1864 (Item 1039)
      - ADDRESS AT A SANITARY FAIR IN PHILADELPHIA ON WAR, THE RELIEF OF SOLDIERS, AND U. S. GRANT, New York World, June 17, 1864 (Item 1006)
      - LINCOLN PROCLAMATION APPOINTING A DAY OF NATIONAL HUMILIATION, FASTING AND PRAYER, The Crisis, July 20, 1864 (Item 1067)
      - LINCOLN PROCLAMATION OF THANKSGIVING AND PRAYER, The Vermont Chronicle, September 10, 1864 (Item 1068)
      - LETTER TO HENRY HOFFMAN ON SLAVERY, Alexandria Gazette, October 11, 1864 (Item 836)
      - LINCOLN PROCLAMATION ON THANKSGIVING, The Crisis, November 23, 1864 (Item 1069)
        As with the above proclamations, and especially with this one, Lincoln exhibits his piety, humility and employment of exalted religious imagery, much as Washington, Adams, and even Madison had in the past on days of fasting and thanksgiving.
        Also JEFFERSON DAVIS' STATE OF THE UNION ADDRESS
      - SERENADE TO PRESIDENT SPEECH AND PASSAGE OF 13TH AMENDMENT, New York Tribune, February 3, 1865 (Item 838)
        In which Lincoln dismisses importance of Emancipation Proclamation.
      - PEACE CONFERENCE NEAR THE END OF THE WAR, New York Tribune, February 11, 1865 (Item 1040)
        Many dispatches signed by Lincoln. Also those of Jefferson Davis, Alexander Stephens, Seward, and Grant.
      - SPEECH TO THE GOVERNOR OF INDIANA AND THE 140TH INDIANA REGIMENT, New York World, March 18, 1865 (Item 1007)
        Comments from Mr. Krause: Given how close it is to the end of the war, Lincoln makes some rather surprisingly uncomplimentary remarks about blacks and their use by the South in the fighting.
      - HIS VERY LAST SPEECH ON THE END OF THE WAR, LOUISIANA RECONSTRUCTION, AND THE BLACK FRANCHISE MADE AT THE WHITE HOUSE ON THE EVENING OF APRIL 11 AND THE FINAL PROCLAMATION CLAIMING EQUALITY OF RIGHTS WITH ALL MARITIME NATIONS, New York Herald, April 12, 1865 (Item 839)
        Comments from Mr. Krause: Lincoln's last words many found uninspiring. His mind was trained on reconstruction, and he hoped to use the example of Louisiana and its constitution as a model for the South. Always the conservative conciliator, he wanted to bring the South back to the fold gently rather than wreak condign punishment on his defeated brethren as the Radical Republicans preferred. In his last speech, Lincoln pushes for a limited black franchise, something no previous president had done. The Fifteenth amendment would pass in 1870. Almost the final words he would speak publically involve an historical mystery, perhaps a message of hope. He said, "In the present situation" as the phrase goes, "it may be my duty to make some new announcement to the people of the South. I am considering, and shall not fail to act, when satisfied that action will be proper." Booth was in the audience and made up his mind then and there.
      - OBSEQUIES AND CEREMONIES FOLLOWING LINCOLN'S ASSASSINATION AND JOHN WILKES BOOTH LETTER EXPLAINING HIS MOTIVES REGARDING LINCOLN, New York Herald, April 20, 1865 (Item 1041)
        See: John Wilkes Booth 1042
      - LETTER FROM LINCOLN TO WADSWORTH ON NEGRO SUFFRAGE, New York Tribune, September 26, 1865 (Item 840)
    - Wendell Phillips
      - ADDRESS ON JOHN BROWN, New York Herald, November 2, 1859 (Item 844)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY LETTER AND HENRY WILSON SPEECH, The Liberator, July 13, 1860 (Item 845)
        Also features advertisement for full report on the proceedings of the Tenth National Woman's Rights Convention.
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH, The Liberator, July 12, 1861 (Item 846)
        Includes William Lloyd Garrison 774
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH, The Liberator, August 9, 1861 (Item 847)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY LECTURE AND GENERAL T. PERRONET THOMPSON SPEECH, The Liberator, January 17, 1862 (Item 848)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH AND BENJAMIN F. WADE SPEECH, The Liberator, May 23, 1862 (Item 849)
        Includes Abraham Lincoln 814
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH AND GERRIT SMITH SPEECH, The Liberator, July 11, 1862 (Item 850)
        Includes David Hunter 778
        Also features "WOMAN AND THE PRESS" proposal for a women's journal by Mary Louise Booth (founding editor of Harper's Bazaar in 1867) and Polish-American doctor Marie Elizabeth Zakrzewska who established women's medical programs and hospitals in the United States).
      - SPEECH/LECTURE ON TOUSSAINT LOUVERTURE, The Liberator, April 3, 1863 (Item 851)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH, The Liberator, May 29, 1863 (Item 852)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH, The Liberator, February 5, 1864 (Item 853)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH AND LINCOLN PROCLAMATION, The Liberator, May 20, 1864 (Item 854)
        Also features Lucretia Mott speech (page 82)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY LETTER AND ELIZABETH CADY STANTON LETTER TO MRS. DALL, The Liberator, June 3, 1864 (Item 855)
      - ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH, New York Herald, May 13, 1865 (Item 856)
    - William T. Sherman
      - OFFICIAL FINAL REPORT ON HIS MARCH FROM ATLANTA TO SAVANNAH, New York Times, June 25, 1865 (Item 1043)
        His own account of the southern campaign.
    - Alexander Stephens
      - CORNERSTONE SPEECH, New York Times, March 27, 1861 (Item 867)
        The definitive explication of racist theology of the South by the vice-president of the Confederacy.
    - Charles Sumner
      - LANDMARK OF FREEDOM SPEECH ON KANSAS-NEBRASKA BILL, New York Daily Tribune, February 22, 1854 (Item 869)
        The first of the triumvirate of great anti-slavery speeches by Sumner.
      - EARLY ANTI-SLAVERY SPEECH BY RADICAL REPUBLICAN SENATOR, New York Daily Times, September 9, 1854 (Item 868)
      - CRIME AGAINST KANSAS SPEECH, AND HIS BEATING BY BROOKS IN THE SENATE, New York Daily Times, May 23, 1856 (Item 870)
        One of the great anti-slavery speeches of the 19th century; his beating was precipitated by the speech and one of landmark events leading to Civil War.
      - BEATING IN THE SENATE AND AFTERMATH, New York Tribune, May 24, 1856 (Item 871)
      - BARBARISM OF SLAVERY SPEECH, New York Herald, June 5, 1860 (Item 872)
        One of the great anti-slavery speeches of 19th century and his first speech upon returning to the Senate.
    - Ben Wade and Winter Davis
      - WADE-DAVIS MANIFESTO, New York Tribune, August 5, 1864 (Item 876)
        Bitter attack on Lincoln by liberal Radical Republicans who want him replaced as President.
  - Native Americans
    - Crazy Horse
      - DEATH OF CRAZY HORSE, American Socialist, September 13, 1877 (Item 757)
        Includes Spotted Tail 866
    - Geronimo
      - PLOT TO MASSACRE GENERAL CROOK AND HIS MEN, Boston Advertiser, April 3, 1886 (Item 775)
    - Chief Joseph
      - SURRENDER OF CHIEF JOSEPH, Warren Mail, October 16, 1877 (Item 784)
      - SURRENDER SPEECH, Harper's Weekly, November 17, 1877; Size: Small (Item 785)
    - Red Cloud
      - SHORT SPEECH AND BIOGRAPHY, New York Tribune, April 30, 1875 (Item 857)
    - Sitting Bull
      - SITTING BULL'S HISTORY AND CUSTER MEMORIAL AND CUSTER DEFENSE, New York Herald, July 20, 1876 (Item 861)
      - SITTING BULL'S SUN DANCE AND GENERALS CROOK AND TERRY AND GRANT'S VIEWS AND BISHOP WHIPPLE ON INDIANS, New York Herald, August 14, 1876 (Item 862)
      - GENERALS CROOK AND TERRY AND CUSTER'S TRAIL AND INDIAN ARMS AND INDIANS CHEATED AND NORTHERN SIOUX, New York Herald, August 18, 1876 (Item 863)
      - SITTING BULL'S FEELINGS TOWARDS WHITES AND GENERALS CROOK AND TERRY AND THE FATE OF THE INDIANS, New York Herald, August 19, 1876 (Item 864)
    - Spotted Tail
      - SHORT SPEECH AND BIOGRAPHY, New York Tribune, April 30, 1875 (Item 865)
        See: Red Cloud 857
      - SHORT SPEECH AND BIOGRAPHY, American Socialist, September 13, 1877 (Item 866)
        See: Crazy Horse 757
- 19th Century American Topics
  - Amistad
    - REPORT ON THE SLAVE SHIP, Philadelphia Inquirer, September 14, 1839 (Item 880)
    - REPORT ON THE TRIALM, United States Gazette, January 11, 1840 (Item 881)
    - TRIAL AND JUDGE'S DECISION, United States Gazette, January 18, 1840 (Item 882)
  - Anti-Slavery, Women's Education and Labor Rights
    - Columns on Anti-Slavery, Women's Education and Labor Rights, Anti-Slavery Bugle, December 8, 1849 (Item 1033)
  - Barbary Pirates
    - EMPEROR OF MOROCCO AND DEY OF ALGIERS DECLARE WAR AGAINST AMERICA, The Balance, August 24, 31, 1802; Size: Small (Item 727)
    - NAPOLEON AND DEY OF ALGIERS EXCHANGE LETTERS, The Balance, November 2, 1802; Size: Small (Item 728)
    - PORTRAIT OF ALGERIA AND DEY OF ALGIERS, The Balance, November 9, 1802; Size: Small (Item 729)
    - DEY OF ALGIERS, The Balance, May 24, 1803; Size: Small (Item 730)
    - COMMENCEMENT OF WAR, The Balance, November 22, 1803; Size: Small (Item 731)
    - GENERAL EATON, The Balance, September 10, 1805; Size: Small (Item 732)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, September 24, 1805; Size: Small (Item 733)
    - CONFIRMATION OF PEACE WITH TRIPOLI, The Balance, October 1, 1805; Size: Small (Item 734)
    - INSURRECTION IN ALGIERS AND DEATH OF JEWISH VIZIER AND KILLING OF JEWS AND TUNIS, The Balance, October 8, 1805; Size: Small (Item 735)
    - TRIPOLI AND TRIPOLITAN TREATY, The Balance, October 22, 1805; Size: Small (Item 736)
    - AMERICAN CAPTIVES IN TRIPOLI, The Balance, October, 29, November 12, 19, 26, December 3, 10, 1805; Size: Small (Item 737)
    - GENERAL EATON IN LIBYA, The Balance, October 29, 1805; Size: Small (Item 738)
    - BEY OF TUNIS, The Balance, November 26, December 3, 1805; Size: Small (Item 739)
    - GENERAL EATON ARRIVES WITH AMBASSADOR AND MURDER AND ROBBERY OF JEWS OF ALGERIA AND DEY OF ALGIERS KILLED, The Balance, December 3, 1805; Size: Small (Item 740)
    - ALGERIAN TURMOIL AND THE JEWS, The Balance, December 10, 1805; Size: Small (Item 741)
    - AMBASSADOR FROM TUNIS AND LATE BASHAW OF TRIPOLI, The Balance, December 24, 1805; Size: Small (Item 742)
  - Judge Chase Impeachment
    - U.S. VERSUS SAMUEL CHASE, The Balance, January 15, 1805; Size: Small (Item 724)
    - SPEECH OF CHASE, The Balance, January 22, 1805; Size: Small (Item 725)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, February 19, March 5, 12, 26, April 2, 1805; Size: Small (Item 726)
  - Colonization
    - EVENTS AND ACTIVITIES, Niles' Weekly Register, January 25, April 12, 1817, June 24, 1820; Size: Small (Item 883)
  - Harry Croswell Trial (versus President Jefferson)
    - INDICTMENTS, The Balance, January 18, 25, 1803; Size: Small (Item 715)
    - ARGUMENTS, The Balance, February 1, 8, 25, 1803; Size: Small (Item 716)
    - LIBERTY OF THE PRESS, The Balance, March 1, 8, 15, 22, April 5, 12, 19, May 3, 10, 1803; Size: Small (Item 717)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, June 7, 14, July 19, August 9, 16, 30, 1803; Size: Small (Item 718)
    - PROCEEDING OF INDICTMENTS, The Balance, July 26, 1803; Size: Small (Item 719)
    - TRIAL AND CROSWELL LETTER, The Balance, September 5, 13, 1803; Size: Small (Item 720)
    - CROSWELL LETTERS, The Balance, October 4, November 1, 1803; Size: Small (Item 721)
    - HAMILTON BECOMES CROSWELL ATTORNEY, The Balance, December 27, 1803; Size: Small (Item 722)
    - ON HIS TRIAL, The Balance, January 22, 1805; Size: Small (Item 723)
  - Federalists versus Republicans
    - ANTI-FEDERALIST ESSAY, National Gazette, March 8, 1792 (Item 676)
      Secretly funded by Jefferson and Madison, the Gazette was the principal organ of opposition to Hamilton, Washington and the Federalist government's agenda and philosophy.
      See: George Washington 579
    - TIRADE AGAINST ARISTOCRATS AND MONOCRATS AND ANTI-RELIGION AND CLERGY AND RAILING AGAINST ENEMIES OF FRANCE, National Gazette, July 18, 1792 (Item 677)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 159
    - AGAINST HAMILTON HANDLING OF DEBT PROBLEM AND ANTI-SPECULATION ESSAY AND ANTI-FEDERALIST ESSAY, National Gazette, October 10, 1792 (Item 678)
    - REDUCING SIZE OF MILITARY AND SATIRE ON NOBILITY AND COURTLINESS OF AMERICAN GOVERNMENT AND AMERICAN SOLDIERS SHOULD BE COMPENSATED AND CELEBRATING IDEAS OF ANTI CONSTITUTIONALISTS AND ANTI-SPECULATION OF CONGRESS AND ANTI-WASHINGTON AND HAMILTON WITH REGARD TO SPECULATION AND CELEBRATION OF FRENCH REVOLUTION AND POSITIVE EFFECTS FOR AMERICA, National Gazette, January 5, 1793 (Item 679)
    - ESSAY CELEBRATING THE FRENCH AND EXECRATING BRITAIN AND THEIR SPECULATING AMERICAN FRIENDS AND PAINE AND BURKE AND DEMOCRATIC (REPUBLICAN) CLUBS TAKING SUBSCRIPTIONS FOR FRANCE AND LETTER EXTOLLING VIRTUES OF REPUBLICANISM AND CONDEMNING EVILS OF FEDERAL MONARCHS, National Gazette, May 4, 1793 (Item 680)
    - AGAINST WASHINGTON'S NEUTRALITY PROCLAMATION AND LIST OF LAFAYETTE'S CRIMES AND RANTING LETTER AGAINST FEDS AND ANTI-FRENCH TRAITORS AND TIRADE AGAINST SPECULATION AND ADDRESS OF CITIZENS TO GENET, National Gazette, May 18, 1793 (Item 681)
    - LETTER TO THE PRESIDENT AND PREPARATIONS FOR GENET'S ARRIVAL AND ANTI-WASHINGTON AND NEUTRALITY PROCLAMATION AND AND DEFENDING LOUIS' DEATH, National Gazette, June 1, 1793 (Item 682)
    - LETTER TO THE PRESIDENT AND AMERICA BEWARE OF BECOMING BRITISH CLONE AND DEFENDING DEATH OF LOUIS AND ANTI-NEUTRALITY PROCLAMATION AND OUR TREATY OBLIGATIONS TO FRANCE, National Gazette, June 5, 1793 (Item 683)
    - LETTER TO THE PRESIDENT AND PRO-FRENCH ANTI-FEDERALIST ESSAY AND OUR TREATY OBLIGATIONS AND ANTI-NEUTRALITY, National Gazette, June 8, 1793 (Item 684)
    - LETTER TO THE PRESIDENT AND PRO-FRENCH AND PRO-TREATY ESSAY AND LETTER ON FRENCH REVOLUTION AND CRITICIZING THOSE WHO CELEBRATED GEORGE III's BIRTHDAY, National Gazette, June 12, 1793 (Item 685)
      See: Toussaint Louverture 408
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, April 6, June 22, 29, July 6, 20, 27, August 3, 10, 24, 31, September 28, October 4, 12, November 23, 1802; Size: Small (Item 686)
    - PRO-PICKERING, The Balance, May 4, 11, 1802; Size: Small (Item 687)
    - JUDGE DEFENDS JUDGES, The Balance, October 19, 1802; Size: Small (Item 688)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, January 4, May 17, August 30, October 11, 18, November 1, 29, 1803; Size: Small (Item 689)
    - EDITORS FROM BOTH SIDES ATTACK, The Balance, February 1, 1803; Size: Small (Item 690)
    - ANTI-ATTORNEY GENERAL SIMPSON FROM NEW YORK AND GOVERNOR CLINTON SPEECH, The Balance, February 22, 1803; Size: Small (Item 691)
    - ALIENS (FOREIGNERS) AND THE SUFFRAGE, The Balance, March 8, 1803; Size: Small (Item 692)
    - NATURALIZATION, The Balance, March 15, 22, 29, April 5, 1803; Size: Small (Item 693)
    - ANTI-MONROE, The Balance, April 5, May 24, 1803; Size: Small (Item 694)
    - ANTI-FRENCH REVOLUTION AND REMOVAL OF FEDS FROM OFFICE ANTI-GALLATIN AND MATTHEW LYON, The Balance, June 14, 21, 1803; Size: Small (Item 695)
    - PRO-FEDERALIST, The Balance, June 28, 1803; Size: Small (Item 696)
    - ANTI-DEMOCRAT, The Balance, August 23, 1803; Size: Small (Item 697)
    - ANTI-JACOBIN (DEMOCRAT), The Balance, September 6, 13, 1803; Size: Small (Item 698)
    - DEMOCRAT TURNS FEDERALIST, The Balance, September 20, 1803; Size: Small (Item 699)
    - ANTI-DEMOCRACY, The Balance, September 27, October 4, 1803; Size: Small (Item 700)
    - CHEETHAM DISCOVERING PLOTS AND CONSPIRACIES, The Balance, January 15, 1805; Size: Small (Item 701)
    - ON DEMOCRACY, The Balance, January 22, February 5, 1805; Size: Small (Item 702)
    - THREE FIFTHS CLAUSE AND SLAVERY, The Balance, February 5, 1805; Size: Small (Item 703)
    - GOVERNOR STRONG'S SPEECH, The Balance, February 12, 1805; Size: Small (Item 704)
    - FIGHTS AMONG DEMOCRATS, The Balance, February 19, September 17, November 19, 1805; Size: Small (Item 705)
    - ANTI-REPUBLICAN, The Balance, March 26, 1805; Size: Small (Item 706)
    - JAMES ELLIOT DEFENDS HIMSELF AGAINST FELLOW DEMOCRATS FOR SOMETIMES SUPPORTING FEDERALIST POLICIES AND DEMOCRACY UNVEILED AND HAMILTON'S LIBEL LAW CELEBRATED BY FEDERALISTS, The Balance, April 23, 1805; Size: Small (Item 707)
    - ON CALLENDER AND JEFFERSON AND THEIR LETTERS AND DEMOCRATIC PRINTERS AND TIRADE AGAINST DEMOCRATS AND JEFFERSON'S ANTI-JEFFERSONIAN WRITINGS, The Balance, April 30, 1805; Size: Small (Item 708)
    - ELLIOT LETTER, The Balance, May 7, 14, 21, 28, June 11, July 2, 9, 16, 1805; Size: Small (Item 709)
    - FREEDOM OF THE PRESS, The Balance, May 14, 1805; Size: Small (Item 710)
    - LYON LETTER, The Balance, July 9, 16, 1805; Size: Small (Item 711)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, July 30, September 10, 1805; Size: Small (Item 712)
    - WHAT FEDERALISTS WANT, The Balance, October 1, 1805; Size: Small (Item 713)
    - ANTI-DEMOCRACY, The Balance, October 22, November 26, December 3, 1805; Size: Small (Item 714)
  - Fort Pillow
    - MASSACRE OF WHITE AND MAINLY BLACK TROOPS AFTER THEY HAD SURRENDERED, The New York Tribune, April 16, 1864 (Item 1057)
      One of the greatest atrocities of the war. Earlier heinous acts committed by the Confederacy and Jefferson Davis' inflammatory language had prompted Lincoln to issue the Order of Retaliation in July 1863 as a response. The implicit threat of a tit-for-tat matter of revenge did not dissuade the rebels from further atrocities. Lincoln never responded in kind. After Fort Pillow, the majority of his cabinet wrote lengthy memos defending retribution, and had the support of most of the northern newspapers. Lincoln never activated the order.
    - REPORT OF THE CONGRESSIONAL COMMITTEE ON THE CONDUCT OF THE WAR OF THE MASSACRE AT FORT PILLOW, The New York Times, May 6, 1864 (Item 1058)
  - Indiana Statehood and Constitution
    - ALLOWING INDIANA TO BECOME A STATE, Niles' Weekly Register, June 1, 1816; Size: Small (Item 986)
      (page 222)
    - CONSTITUTION OF INDIANA, Niles' Weekly Register, August 17, 1816; Size: Small (Item 987)
      (page 404)
    - INDIANA JOINS THE UNION, National Intelligencer, December 7, 1816 (Item 988)
  - Louisiana Territory and Purchase
    - SPAIN CEDES LOUISIANA TO FRANCE, The Balance, April 6, October 19, 1802; Size: Small (Item 646)
    - GENERAL BERNADOTTE TO CREATE A MILITARY COLONY IN LOUISIANA COMPRISED OF BLACK REBELS AND CRIMINALS IN ALLIANCE WITH KENTUCKY AND TENNESSEE, The Balance, June 15, 1802; Size: Small (Item 647)
    - THE PRESIDENT'S MESSAGE AND LOUISIANA, The Balance, January 4, 11, 18, 1803; Size: Small (Item 648)
      See: Thomas Jefferson 278 (January 4)
    - CONGRESS AND LOUISIANA AND NEW ORLEANS, The Balance, February 1, 1803; Size: Small (Item 649)
    - CONGRESS AND LOUISIANA, The Balance, February 8, 15, March 1, 15, 22, April 19, 1803; Size: Small (Item 650)
    - MISCELLANEOUS, The Balance, March 29, May 3, 10, 1803; Size: Small (Item 651)
    - PROCLAMATION OF FRENCH GOVERNOR OF LOUISIANA, The Balance, May 17, 1803; Size: Small (Item 652)
    - DEPOSIT IN NEW ORLEANS ALLOWED, The Balance, June 28, 1803; Size: Small (Item 653)
    - LOUISIANA CEDED TO UNITED STATES, The Balance, July 5, 1803; Size: Small (Item 654)